I should tell you that when I was asked to be here,
أود أن أخبركم بأنه عندما تمت دعوتي للحضور
I thought to myself that well, it's TED.
فكرت أن هذا جيد , إنه تيد
And these TEDsters are -- you know, as innocent as that name sounds --
وهؤلاء أعضاء تيد هم - تعرفون ، بقدر ما ينُم الإسم عن البساطه..
these are the philanthropists and artists and scientists who sort of shape our world.
فأنهم هم المحسنين والفنانين والعلماء الذين يشكلون عالمنا
And what could I possibly have to say that would be distinguished enough
وما الذي يمكن أن أقول ليكون مميزاً بما يكفي
to justify my participation in something like that?
ليبرز أهليتي للمشاركه في مثل هذا الحدث
And so I thought perhaps a really civilized-sounding British accent
وهكذا فكرت ربما يجب ان استخدم لكنه بريطانيه متحضره
might help things a bit.
والتي قد تساعد بعض الشئ
And then I thought no, no. I should just get up there and be myself
وبعدها فكرت لا ، لا . يجب أن أصعد إلي هناك و أكون كما أنا
and just talk the way I really talk
وأتكلم بنفس طريقتي الحقيقيه في الحديث
because, after all, this is the great unveiling.
لأنه ، بعد كل شئ ، هذا هو الكشف العظيم
And so I thought I'd come up here and unveil my real voice to you.
و فكرت أن أتي هنا وأكشف عن صوتي الحقيقي لكم
Although many of you already know that I do speak the Queen's English
رغم أن الكثيرين منكم يعرفون مسبقاً بأني أتحدث بلكنة ملكة انجلترا
because I am from Queens, New York.
لأنني من كوينز نيويورك .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But the theme of this session, of course, is invention.
لكن موضوع هذه الجلسه، بالطبع، هو الإختراع.
And while I don't have any patents that I'm aware of,
ومع عدم إمتلاكي لأي من البراءات علي حد علمي ،
you will be meeting a few of my inventions today.
سوف تلتقون بعض من إختراعاتي اليوم .
I suppose it's fair to say
وأعتقد أنه من المنصف أن أقول
that I am interested in the invention of self or selves.
أنني مهتمه بإختراعات النفس أو الأنفس .
We're all born into certain circumstances with particular physical traits,
جميعنا وُلدنا في ظروف معينه بصفات فيزيائه محدده
unique developmental experiences, geographical and historical contexts.
تجارب تنمويه فريده ، وسياقات جغرافيه وتاريخيه .
But then what?
لكن ماذا بعد ؟
To what extent do we self-construct, do we self-invent?
لأي مدي نقوم ببناء ذاتنا و إختراعها ؟
How do we self-identify and how mutable is that identity?
كيف نُعرف ذاتنا و كم هي متقلبه تلك الهويه ؟
Like, what if one could be anyone at any time?
مثلاً ، ماذا لو أن الشخص بإمكانه أن يصبح اي شخص في اي وقت ؟
Well my characters, like the ones in my shows,
حسناً شخصياتي ، مثل التي في عروضي
allow me to play with the spaces between those questions.
تسمح لي بأن ألعب بالمساحات بين تلك الأسئله
And so I've brought a couple of them with me.
وعليه فلقد أحضرت البعض معي
And well, they're very excited.
و هم متحمسين جداً
What I should tell you --
ما أود أن أقوله لكم
what I should tell you is that they've each prepared their own little TED talks.
ما أود أن أقوله لكم أن كل منهم قد أعد خطابه الخاص لتيد
So feel free to think of this as Sarah University.
فخذو راحتكم في التفكير في هذا كجامعه ساره
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Okay. Okay. Oh, well.
حسناً . حسناً . أوه ،
Oh, wonderful.
أوه ، رائع.
Good evening everybody.
مساء الخير جميعاً .
Thank you so very much for having me here today.
أشكركم جزيل الشكر لإستضافتي هنا اليوم .
Ah, thank you very much. My name is Lorraine Levine.
آآ ، شكراً جزيلاً لكم ، إسمي لورين ليفين.
Oh my! There's so many of you.
أوه عجباً ، هناك الكثير منكم .
Hi sweetheart. Okay.
مرحباً عزيزتي . حسناً .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
Anyway, I am here because of a young girl, Sarah Jones.
أنا هنا بفضل فتاه شابه ، ساره جونز .
She's a very nice, young black girl.
هي فتاه لطيفه جداً ، شابه ، سوداء
Well you know, she calls herself black --
تعرفون ، تدعو نفسها سوداء
she's really more like a caramel color if you look at her.
هي اشبه بلون الكاراميل لو نظرت إليها .
But anyway.
لكن علي اي حال
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
She has me here because she puts me in her show,
أحضرتني هنا لأنضم إلي عرضها
what she calls her one-woman show.
الذي تدعوه عرض المرأه الواحده
And you know what that means, of course.
وتعرفون ما يعنيه ذلك، بالطبع .
That means she takes the credit and then makes us come out here and do all the work.
يعني أنها تنسب الفضل لها بينما تجعلنا نأتي هنا ونقوم بالعمل كله .
But I don't mind.
لكنني لا أمانع .
Frankly, I'm kvelling just to be here
بصراحه ،أنا فخوره بأن أكون هنا
with all the luminaries you have attending something like this, you know.
مع كل النجوميه التي تكتسبها بحضورشئ مثل هذا ، تعلمون .
Really, it's amazing.
حقيقيه ، أنه أمر مدهش.
Not only, of course, the scientists and all the wonderful giants of the industries
ليس فقط ، بالطبع ، العلماء و جميع عمالقه الصناعات
but the celebrities.
ولكن المشاهير .
There are so many celebrities running around here.
هناك الكثير من المشاهير يحومون هنا .
I saw -- Glenn Close I saw earlier. I love her.
لقد رايت - غلين كلوز باكراً. أنا أحبها .
And she was getting a yogurt in the Google cafe.
كانت تأخذ الزبادي في مقهي قوقل .
Isn't that adorable?
أليس ذلك محبباً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So many others you see, they're just wonderful.
وأخرين كثر تراهم ، إنهم رائعين .
It's lovely to know they're concerned, you know.
من الجميل أن تعرف أنهم مهتمون ، تعلمون .
And -- oh, I saw Goldie Hawn.
و ... أوه ، لقد رأيت قولدي هآن .
Oh, Goldie Hawn. I love her, too; she's wonderful. Yeah.
أوه ، قولدي هآن أحبها أيضاً ، هي رائعه . نعم.
You know, she's only half Jewish.
تعلمون ، نصف نسبها فقط يهودي .
Did you know that about her?
هل كنتم تعرفون هذا عنها ؟
Yeah. But even so, a wonderful talent. (Laughter)
نعم ، لكن برغم ذلك ، موهبه رائعه .
And I -- you know, when I saw her, such a wonderful feeling.
و أنا .. تعلمون ،عندما رأيتها ، أنتابني شعور رائع .
Yeah, she's lovely.
نعم ، هي محببه .
But anyway, I should have started by saying just how lucky I feel.
لكن علي كل حال ، كان يجب أن أبدا بقولي كم أشعر باني محظوظه.
It's such an eye-opening experience to be here.
إن وجودي هنا تجربه مُبصّره
You're all so responsible for this world that we live in today.
جميعكم مسؤولون عن هذا العالم الذي نعيش فيه اليوم
You know, I couldn't have dreamed of such a thing as a young girl.
تعلمون ، ما كنت لأحلم بشئ مماثل عندما كنت شابه.
And you've all made these advancements happen in such a short time --
وقد قمتم بتحقيق كل هذا التقدم خلال هذا الوقت القصير
you're all so young.
جميعكم شباب .
You know, your parents must be very proud.
تعلمون ، لا بد أن أهلكم فخورين بكم للغايه .
But I -- I also appreciate the diversity that you have here.
لكن أنا .. أيضاً أقدر التنوع الذي بينكم هنا .
I noticed it's very multicultural.
لقد لاحظت أنه فعلاً متعدد الثقافات.
You know, when you're standing up here, you can see all the different people.
تعلمون ، عندما تقف هنا تستطيع أن تري جميع الناس المختلفين .
It's like a rainbow.
إنه كقوس قزح.
It's okay to say rainbow. Yeah.
من المقبول أن أقول قوس قزح . نعم .
I just -- I can't keep up with whether you can say, you know, the different things.
أنا فقط .. لا استطيع مواكبه ما الذي يمكنك قوله ، تعلمون ، جميع الأشياء المختلفه .
What are you allowed to say or not say?
ما الذي يسمح لك بأن تقول أو لا تقول ؟
I just -- I don't want to offend anybody. You know.
أنا فقط .. لا أريد أن أسئ لأي شخص . تعلمون .
But anyway, you know,
لكن علي اي حال ، تعلمون ،
I just think that to be here with all of you
أنا فقط أعتقد بوجودي هنا معكم جميعاً
accomplished young people --
الشباب البارعون.
literally, some of you, the architects building our brighter future.
بالفعل ، بعضكم ، هم المهندسون الذين يبنون مستقبلنا المشرق
You know, it's heartening to me.
تعلمون ، هو مشجع لي
Even though, quite frankly, some of your presentations are horrifying,
بالرغم من ، صراحهً ، بعض العروض مروعه.
absolutely horrifying.
بالفعل مروعه .
It's true. It's true.
هي حقيقيه .هي حقيقيه .
You know, between the environmental degradation
تعلمون بين التدهور البيئي
and the crashing of the world markets you're talking about.
وإنهيار السوق العالمي الذي تتحدثون عنه
And of course, we know it's all because of the -- all the ...
وبالطبع ، نعلم أن هذا كله بسبب ال.. كل ال...
Well, I don't know how else to say it to you, so I'll just say it my way:
حسناً، لا أعلم أي طريقه أخرى لأقولها لكم ، لذلك سوف أقولها بطريقتي .
the ganeyvish schticklich coming from the governments and the, you know,
الأنشطه المستتره من الحكومات وال.. تعلمون
the bankers and the Wall Street. You know it.
والبنكيون ، و ووال سترييت .تعرفونه.
Anyway.
علي كل حال .
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
The point is, I'm happy somebody has practical ideas
المغزي هو ، أنا سعيده أن للبعض أفكار عمليه
to get us out of this mess.
لتخرجنا من هذه الفوضي
So I salute each of you and your stellar achievements.
لذلك أحيي كل منكم و إنجازاتكم الممتازه
Thank you for all that you do.
شكراً لكل ما تفعلون
And congratulations on being such big makhers that you've become TED meisters.
وتهانئ لكونكم أصبحتم بارعين جدا لتغدوا خبراء تيد
So, happy continued success.
كذلك ، نجاح متواصل سعيد.
Congratulations. Mazel tov.
تهانئ. حظ سعيد.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Hi. Hi.
مرحبا. مرحبا.
Thank you everybody.
شكراً لكم جميعاً.
Sorry, this is such a wonderful opportunity and everything, to be here right now.
عذراً، هذه فرصه رائعه وكل شئ ،أن أكون هنا الأن.
My name is Noraida. And I'm just --
إسمي نوريدا. وأنا فقط..
I'm so thrilled to be part of like your TED conference
انا متحمسه جدا أن أشارك في من مؤتمركم تيد
that you're doing and everything like that.
الذي تقومون به و أي شئ أخر مثله.
I am Dominican-American.
أنا دومنيكيه أمريكيه .
Actually, you could say I grew up in the capital of Dominican Republic,
في الواقع ، يمكن أن تقول أنني نشأت في عاصمه الجمهوريه الدونميكيه.
otherwise known as Washington Heights in New York City.
بشكل أخر تُعرف بواشنطن هايتس في مدينه نيويورك .
But I don't know if there's any other Dominican people here,
لكني لا أعرف إذا كان هنالك أي دومينيكيين هنا .
but I know that Juan Enriquez, he was here yesterday.
لكن أعرف أن خوان إنريكيز كان بالأمس هنا.
And I think he's Mexican, so that's --
وأعتقد أنه مكسيسكي، وذلك ..
honestly, that's close enough for me right now. So --
صدقاً، هذا قريب كفايه بالنسبه لي ، حالياً.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
I just -- I'm sorry.
أنا فقط..أعذروني.
I'm just trying not to be nervous because this is
أحاول فقط أن لا أكون متوتره لأن هذه
a very wonderful experience for me and everything.
تجربه رائعه لي وكل شئ .
And I just -- you know I'm not used to doing the public speaking.
و فقط..لست معتاده علي إلقاء الخطب.
And whenever I get nervous I start to talk really fast.
وعندما أتوتر أبدأ بالحديث بسرعه شديده.
Nobody can understand nothing I'm saying, which is very frustrating for me,
لا أحد يستطيع أن يفهم شئياً مما أقول،وهوما يحبطني للغايه.
as you can imagine.
كما يمكن أن تتخيلوا
I usually have to just like try to calm down and take a deep breath.
عاده أحاول أنا أهدأ وأخذ نفس عميق.
But then on top of that, you know, Sarah Jones told me we only have 18 minutes.
لكن بالإضافه إلي ذلك ، تعلمون، ساره جونز أخبرتني أن لدينا 18 دقيقه فقط.
So then I'm like, should I be nervous, you know, because maybe it's better.
ولذلك أنا،يجب أن أكون متوتره، تعلمون، هذا أفضل ربما.
And I'm just trying not to panic and freak out. So I like, take a deep breath.
وأحاول فقط أن لا أذعر وأرتعب. وهكذا ، أخذ نفس عميق.
Okay. Sorry. So anyway, what I was trying to say is that I really love TED.
حسناً. عذراً. علي أي حال، ما أحاول قوله أنني فعلاً أحب تيد.
Like, I love everything about this. It's amazing.
مثل، أحب كل شئ حوله. إنه مذهل.
Like, it's -- I can't get over this right now.
مثل، هو.. لا أستطيع أن أتغلب علي شعوري هذا الأن.
And, like, people would not believe, seriously, where I'm from,
و، مثل، لن يصدق الناس ، فعلاً، من حيث أتيت ،
that this even exists.
إن هذا موجود حتى
You know, like even, I mean I love like the name, the -- TED.
تعلمون، مثل حتى ، أقصد أحب الإسم، ال.. تيد
I mean I know it's a real person and everything, but I'm just saying that like,
أقصد أعرف أنه شخص حقيقي و كل شئ ، لكنني فقط أقول ذلك.
you know, I think it's very cool how it's also an acronym, you know,
تعلمون، أظنه مميز أنه أيضاً إختصار ، تعلمون،
which is like, you know, is like very high concept and everything like that.
وهو مثل ، تعلمون ، مثل مفهوم عالي جداً وكل شئ .
I like that.
يعجبني هذا.
And actually, I can relate to the whole like acronym thing and everything.
وفي الواقع، يمكن أن تكون لي علاقه بالإختصارات وكل شئ .
Because, actually, I'm a sophomore at college right now.
لأنني ، طالبه في الكليه حالياً.
At my school -- actually I was part of co-founding an organization,
وفي كليتي .. في الواقع أنني عضو مشارك في تأسيس منظمه
which is like a leadership thing,
وهو شئ مثل القياده.
you know, like you guys, you would really like it and everything.
تعلمون، مثلكم أعزائي،سوف تحبونه وكل شئ.
And the organization is called DA BOMB,
والمنظمه تُدعي ذا بآم
A\and DA BOMB -- not like what you guys can build and everything --
و ذا بآم .. ليست مثل التي يمكن تركيبها و كل شئ
it's like, DA BOMB, it means like Dominican -- it's an acronym --
هي مثل، ذا بآم، معناها مثل الدومنيكين.. هي إختصار
Dominican-American Benevolent Organization for Mothers and Babies.
المنظمه الخيريه الدومينيكيه الأمريكيه للمرأه والطفل
So, I know, see, like the name is like a little bit long,
كذلك ، أعلم ، ترون ، كأن الإسم طويل قليلاً.
but with the war on terror and everything,
لكن مع الحرب ضد الإرهاب وكل شئ.
the Dean of Student Activities has asked us to stop saying DA BOMB
أمرنا عميد الطلاب بأن نتوقف عن قول ذا بآم
and use the whole thing so nobody would get the wrong idea, whatever.
وأن نستخدم الإسم كاملاً بحيث لا يأخذ أي أحد فكره خاطئه، أياً كان.
So, basically like DA BOMB --
هكذا، أساساً مثل ذا بآم..
what Dominican-American Benevolent Organization for Mothers and Babies does
ما تفعله المنظمه الخيريه الدومينيكيه الأمريكيه للمرأه والطفل
is, basically, we try to advocate for students who show a lot of academic promise
هو، أساساً، نحاول أن ندافع عن الطلاب الذين يظهرون لديهم أكاديميات واعده
and who also happen to be mothers like me.
واللأئي هن أمهات أيضاً مثلي.
I am a working mother, and I also go to school full-time.
أنا أم عامله، وطالبه بدوام كامل.
And, you know, it's like -- it's so important to have like role models out there.
و ، تعلمون ، إنه مثل.. من المهم أن يكون هنالك قدوه.
I mean, I know sometimes our lifestyles are very different, whatever.
أعني ، بعض الأحيان تكون أنماط حياتنا مختلفه جداً، أياً كان.
But like even at my job -- like, I just got promoted.
لكن حتي في عملي ..مثل ، لقد ترقيت لتوي.
Right now it's very exciting actually for me
حالياً أنا مبتهجه جداً في الواقع
because I'm the Junior Assistant to the Associate Director
أصبحت المساعد الجديد للمدير
under the Senior Vice President for Business Development --
تحت نائب الرئيس الأول لتطوير الأعمال
that's my new title.
هذا هو لقبي الجديد
So, but I think whether you own your own company or you're just starting out like me,
هكذا، لكنني أعتقد سواء كنت تملك شركتك الخاصه أو أنت مبتدئ مثلي.
like something like this is so vital
مثل شئ حيوي كهذا
for people to just continue expanding their minds and learning.
فقط لكي يستمر الناس بتوسيع أفاقاهم و تعلمهم
And if everybody, like all people really had access to that,
وإذا تمكن كل شخص، مثل الجميع بالوصول إلي ذلك.
it would be a very different world out there, as I know you know.
سيكون العالم مختلفاً جداً، كما أعلم أنكم تعلمون.
So, I think all people, we need that,
وهكذا، أعتقد أن جميع الناس ، نحتاج ذلك،
but especially, I look at people like me, you know like,
لكن علي وجه الخصوص، أنظر إلي الأشخاص مثلي، تعلمون مثل
I mean, Latinos -- we're about to be the majority, in like two weeks.
أعني، اللاتينيين، نحن علي وشك أن نشكل الأغلبيه،خلال أسبوعين تقريباً.
So, we deserve just as much to be part of the exchange of ideas as everybody else.
ونستحق بنفس القدر مثل الجميع أن نشارك في تبادل الأفكار
So, I'm very happy that you're, you know, doing this kind of thing,
وأنا سعيده لأننا كذلك، تعلمون، نفعل هذا الشئ.
making the talks available online.
نجعل المحادثات متاحه علي الإنترنت
That's very good. I love that.
هذا جيد جداً. أنا أحب ذلك.
And I just -- I love you guys. I love TED.
وأنا فقط.. أحبكم أعزائي. أحب تيد.
And if you don't mind, privately now, in the future, I'm going to think of TED
وإن لم تمانعو، بشكل خاص الأن، في المستقبل، سأفكر في تيد
as an acronym for Technology, Entertainment and Dominicans.
كإختصار للتكنولوجيا، التسليه والدومنيكيين.
Thank you very much.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
So, that was Noraida,
كانت تلك نوريدا.
and just like Lorraine and everybody else you're meeting today,
ومثل لورين و جميع الذين سوف تلتقونهم اليوم.
these are folks who are based on real people from my real life:
هي شخصيات مبنيه علي شخصيات حقيقيه في حياتي.
friends, neighbors, family members.
أصدقاء، جيران، أقرباء.
I come from a multicultural family.
أتيت من عائله متعدده الثقافات
In fact, the older lady you just met:
في الحقيقه السيده المسنه التي التقيتموها للتو،
very, very loosely based on a great aunt on my mother's side.
بتصرف كبير جداً جداً مستوحاه من عمه كبيره من جهه أمي.
It's a long story, believe me.
هذه قصه طويله ، صدقوني.
But on top of my family background,
لكن بالاضافه إلى خلفيه عائلتي.
my parents also sent me to the United Nations school,
أرسلني والداي إلى مدرسه الأمم المتحده،
where I encountered a plethora of new characters,
حيث قابلت مجموعه كبيره من الشخصيات الجديده.
including Alexandre, my French teacher, okay.
بما فيهم إلكسندر ، أستاذه اللغه الفرنسيه ، حسناً.
Well, you know, it was beginner French, that I am taking with her, you know.
حسناً،تعلمون ، كانت تعلم الفرنسيه للمبتدئين ، تعلمون.
And it was Madame Bousson, you know, she was very [French].
كانت مدام بوسون، تعلمون، كانت فرنسيه للغايه.
It was like, you know, she was there in the class,
كانت مثل، تعلمون، هناك في الصف،
you know, she was kind of typically French.
تعلمون، كانت فرنسيه كالعادةً .
You know, she was very chic, but she was very filled with ennui, you know.
تعلمون، كانت أنيقه جداً، لكن ممله، تعلمون.
And she would be there, you know, kind of talking with the class, you know,
وتكون هناك ، تعلمون، تتحدث مع الصف، تعلمون.
talking about the, you know, the existential futility of life, you know.
وتتحدث عن، تعلمون، العبث الوجودي للحياه، تعلمون.
And we were only 11 years old, so it was not appropriate. (Laughter)
ونحن فقط في الحاديه عشر من العمر، وذلك لم يكن مناسباً.
But [German].
لكن الألمانيه.
Yes, I took German for three years, [German],
نعم، أخذت الألمانيه لمده ثلاث سنوات
and it was quite the experience because I was the only black girl in the class,
وكانت تجربه مميزه لكوني الفتاه السوداء الوحيده في الصف.
even in the UN school.
حتي في مدرسه الأمم المتحده.
Although, you know, it was wonderful.
رغم ذلك، تعلمون، كانت رائعه.
The teacher, Herr Schtopf, he never discriminated.
المعلم، هر سكتوبف، لم يكن يتعامل بعنصريه
Never. He always, always treated each of us,
أبداً، كان دائماً، دائماً يعامل كل منا،
you know, equally unbearably during the class.
تعلمون، بنفس القدر بشكل لا يطاق خلال الدرس.
So, there were the teachers and then there were my friends,
هكذا، كان هناك المعلمون ثم كان هناك أصدقائي.
classmates from everywhere,
زملاء الصف من كل مكان.
many of whom are still dear friends to this day.
كثيرون منهم ما زالوا أصدقاء أعزاء حتي اليوم.
And they've inspired many characters as well.
و قد أوحوا لي بكثير من الشخصيات أيضاً.
For example, a friend of mine.
مثلاً، صديقه لي.
Well, I just wanted to quickly say good evening.
حسناً، أردت فقط أن أقول بسرعة مساء الخير.
My name is Praveen Manvi and thank you very much for this opportunity.
إسمي برافين مانفي وأشكركم كثيراً علي هذه الفرصه.
Of course, TED, the reputation precedes itself all over the world.
بالطبع، تيد، الصيت يسابق نفسه في جميع أنحاء العالم.
But, you know, I am originally from India,
لكن، تعلمون، أنا أصلاً من الهند.
and I wanted to start by telling you
وأود أن أبدأ بأن أخبركم
that once Sarah Jones told me that we will be having the opportunity
أنه عندما أخبرتني ساره جونز بهذه الفرصه
to come here to TED in California,
للحضور هنا إلي تيد في كالفورنيا.
originally, I was very pleased and, frankly, relieved
في الأصل،لقد سررت جدا، بصراحه، شعرت بالراحه
because, you know, I am a human rights advocate.
لأنه، تعلمون، أنني محاميه لحقوق الإنسان
And usually my work, it takes me to Washington D.C.
وعاده عملي، يأخذني إلي واشنطن
And there, I must attend these meetings, mingling with some tiresome politicians,
وهناك، يجب أن أحضر كل تلك الإجتماعات والإختلاط مع بعض السياسيين المملين،
trying to make me feel comfortable
يحاولون أن يشعرونني بالراحه
by telling how often they are eating the curry in Georgetown. (Laughter)
بأن يخبروني كيف أنهم غالباً ما يتناولون الكاري في جورج تاون.
So, you can just imagine -- right.
يمكنكم فقط أن تتخيلو ذلك... صحيح.
So, but I'm thrilled to be joining all of you here.
لكنني سعيده بالإنضمام اليكم هنا.
I wish we had more time together, but that's for another time. Okay? Great.
وددت لو كان لدينا مزيد من الوقت معاً، لكن هذا لوقت أخر. موافقون؟ عظيم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
And, sadly, I don't think we'll have time for you to meet everybody I brought, but --
للأسف، لا أعتقد بأن لدينا وقت لنقابل جميع من أحضرت معي ، لكن..
I'm trying to behave myself,
أحاول أن أتصرف بتهذيب
it's my first time here.
هي المره الأولي لي هنا.
But I do want to introduce you to a couple of folks you may recognize,
لكنني أود أن أقدم لكم بعض الشخصيات التي ربما تتعرفون عليها
if you saw "Bridge and Tunnel."
إذا كنتم رأيتم "الجسر والنفق"
Uh, well, thank you.
أوه، حسناً، شكراً لكم.
Good evening.
مساء الخير.
My name is Pauline Ning,
أسمي بولين نينج.
and first I want to tell you that I'm --
أود أولاً أن أخبركم بأنني..
of course I am a member of the Chinese community in New York.
بالطبع أنا عضوه في المجتمع الصيني في نيويورك.
But when Sarah Jones asked me to please come to TED,
لكن عندما طلبت مني ساره جونز الحضور إلي تيد.
I said, well, you know, first, I don't know that, you know --
قلت، حسناً، تعلمون، أولاً، لا أعرف ذلك، تعلمون..
before two years ago, you would not find me in front of an audience of people,
منذ سنتين خلت ،لم تكونو لتلتقوني أمام جمهور من الناس
much less like this
أقل بكثير من هذا
because I did not like to give speeches
لأنني لا أحب إلقاء الخطب
because I feel that, as an immigrant, I do not have good English skills for speaking.
لأنني أشعر أنني كمهاجره لا أمتلك مهارات جيده للتحدث بالإنجليزيه
But then, I decided, just like Governor Arnold Schwarzenegger,
لكنني، قررت، فقط مثل الحاكم أرنولد شوارزنجر،
I try anyway.
أن أحاول علي أي حال.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
My daughter -- my daughter wrote that,
إبنتي.. إبنتي كتبت هذا،
she told me, "Always start your speech with humor."
أخبرتني " ابدئي حديثك دائماً بنكته."
But my background --
لكن خلفيتي..
I want to tell you story only briefly.
سأخبركم حكايه بإختصار.
My husband and I, we brought our son and daughter here in 1980s
زوجي وأنا أحضرنا أبني وإبنتي هنا عام 1980
to have the freedom we cannot have in China at that time.
لنحصل علي الحريه التي لم تتوفر في الصين في ذلك الوقت.
And we tried to teach our kids to be proud of their tradition, but it's very hard.
وقد حاولنا أن نعلم أولادنا أن يفخروا بتقاليدهم، لكنه صعب جدا .
You know, as immigrant, I would speak Chinese to them,
تعلمون، كمهاجر، أتحدث إليهم بالصينيه،
and they would always answer me back in English.
ودائماً يجاوبونني بالإنجليزيه.
They love rock music, pop culture, American culture.
يحبون موسيقي الروك، ثقافه البوب، الثقافه الأمريكيه.
But when they got older,
لكن عندما كبروا،
when the time comes for them to start think about getting married,
عندما حان الوقت لكي يبدأوا بالتفكير في الزواج.
that's when we expect them to realize, a little bit more, their own culture.
حينها توقعنا منهم أن يدركوا، أكثر ، ثقافتهم.
But that's where we had some problems.
لكن عند ذلك وأجهنا بعض المشاكل.
My son, he says he is not ready to get married.
إبني، يقول أنه غير مستعد للزواج
And he has a sweetheart, but she is American woman, not Chinese.
ولديه حبيبه، لكنها إمرأه أمريكيه، وليست صينيه.
It's not that it's bad, but I told him, "What's wrong with a Chinese woman?"
ليس هذا سيئاً، لكنني أخبرته، " ما هو عيب المرأه الصينيه"
But I think he will change his mind soon.
لكنني أعتقد أنه سوف يغير رأيه قريباً.
So, then I decide instead, I will concentrate on my daughter.
عندها قررت بالمقابل أن أركز علي إبنتي
The daughter's marriage is very special to the mom.
زواج الإبنه خاص جداً بالنسبه للأم
But first, she said she's not interested.
لكن أولاً، قالت بأنه لا رغبه لديها.
She only wants to spend time with her friends.
تريد فقط أن تقضي الوقت مع أصدقائها.
And then at college, it's like she never came home.
بعدها في الكليه، لم تعد تأتي إلي المنزل.
And she doesn't want me to come and visit.
وهي لا تريدني أن أزورها.
So I said, "What's wrong in this picture?"
وهكذا سألتها، " ما العيب في هذه الصوره"
So, I accused my daughter to have like a secret boyfriend.
إتهمتها بأن لديها حبيب سري
But she told me, "Mom, you don't have to worry about boys
لكنها أخبرتني " أمي لا تقلقي حيال الأولاد،
because I don't like them."
لأنني لا أحبهم"
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
And I said, "Yes, men can be difficult, but all women have to get used to that."
وقلت، " نعم الرجال قد يكونوا صعبين، لكن يجب أن تعتاد جميع النساء على ذلك"
She said, "No Mom. I mean, I don't like boys. I like girls.
قالت، " لا يا امي، أقصد، انا لا أحب الأولاد. أحب البنات"
I am lesbian."
أنا سحاقيه.
So, I always teach my kids to respect American ideas,
دائماً ما أعلم أولادي إحترام الأفكار الأمريكيه.
but I told my daughter that this is one exception --
لكنني أخبرت إبنتي إن هذا إستثناء
(Laughter) --
(ضحك)
that she is not gay, she is just confused by this American problem.
هي ليست مثليه، هي فقط مشوشه بهذه المشكله الأمريكيه.
But she told me, "Mom, it's not American."
لكنها أخبرتني، "أمي هذه ليست أمريكيه"
She said she is in love -- in love with a nice Chinese girl.
قالت إنها واقعه في الحب ، مع فتاه صينيه جميله.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
So, these are the words I am waiting to hear,
هكذا، تلك هي الكلمات التي إنتظرت سماعها،
but from my son, not my daughter.
لكن من إبني، ليس من إبنتي.
(Laughter)
(ضحك)
But at first I did not know what to do.
لكن في البدايه لم أعرف ما علي فعله.
But then, over time, I have come to understand that this is who she is.
لكن بعدها، بمرور الوقت، وصلت إلي أن أتفهم أن هذه هي حقيقتها.
So, even though sometimes it's still hard,
برغم أنها ما زالت صعبه بعض الأحيان
I will share with you that it helps me to realize
ساشرككم في أن ذلك ساعدني لأدرك
society is more tolerant, usually because of places like this,
أن المجتمع أكثر تسامحاً، بسبب أماكن مثل هذا المكان
because of ideas like this,
وأفكار مثل هذه
and people like you, with an open mind.
وأشخاص مثلكم، بعقول متفتحه.
So I think maybe TED, you impact people's lives
أعتقد أن تيد ربما ، تؤثرون على حياه الناس
in the ways maybe even you don't realize.
باشكال ربما لا تدركونها
So, for my daughter's sake,
لذلك، لأجل إبنتي،
I thank you for your ideas worth spreading.
أشكركم لأفكاركم التي تستحق النشر.
Thank you. Xie xie.
أشكركم .
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Good evening. My name is Habbi Belahal.
مساء الخير، إسمي حبيبه رحال.
And I would like to first of all thank Sarah Jones
وأود أولاً أن أشكر ساره جونز
for putting all of the pressure on the only Arab who she brought with her
لوضعها كل الضغط علي أنا - العربيه الوحيده التي أحضرتها معها
to be last today.
لتكون الأخيره اليوم.
I am originally from Jordan.
في الأصل أنا من الأردن.
And I teach comparative literature at Queens College.
وأعلم الأدب المقارن في كليه كوينز.
It is not Harvard.
هي ليست هارفرد.
But I feel a bit like a fish out of water.
رغم أني أحس قليلاً كأنني سمكه خارج الماء.
But I am very proud of my students.
لكنني فخوره جداً بطلابي.
And I see that a few of them did make it here to the conference.
وأرى بعضهم إستطاعوا الحضور للمؤتمر.
So you will get the extra credit I promised you.
ستحصلون علي علامات زياده أعدكم.
But, while I know that I may not look like the typical TED-izen, as you would say,
لكن ، أعلم انني لا أبدو كمقيمه نموذجيه ، كما يمكنكم القول،
I do like to make the point that we in global society,
أود أن أوضح وجهه نظري بأننا في مجتمع عالمي
we are never as different as the appearances may suggest.
لسنا مختلفين أبداً كما قد توحي مظاهرنا
So, if you will indulge me, I will share quickly with you a bit of verse,
لذلك ، لو أمهلتموني لأشارككم بسرعه بمقطع شعري
which I memorized as a young girl at 16 years of age.
حفظته وانا شابه في السادسه عشر من العمر
So, back in the ancient times.
قديماً في العصور الغابره.
[Arabic]
عربي
And this roughly translates:
وهذا يترجم تقريباً
"Please, let me hold your hand.
ارجوك أن تدعني أمسك يدك
I want to hold your hand.
أريد أن أمسك بيدك
And when I touch you, I feel happy inside.
عندما أمسك بيدك،يفرح قلبي.
It's such a feeling that my love, I can't hide, I can't hide, I can't hide."
أنا سعيده جدا ، يا حبي ، لا أستطيع أن أخفيه، لا أستطيع أن أخفيه
Well, so okay, but please, please, but please.
حسناً،لكن أرجوكم، أرجوكم.
If it is sounding familiar, it is because I was at the same time in my life
إذا كان يبدو مألوفاً فلأنني كنت في نفس الفتره
listening to the Beatles.
أستمع إلي البيتلز.
On the radio [unclear], they were very popular.
في الراديو،كانو مشهورين جداً.
So, all of that is to say that I like to believe
وكل هذا لأقول أنني أود أن أصدق،
that for every word intended as to render us deaf to one another,
أنه لكل كلمه يهدف بها تقديم أحدنا للأخر كصم
there is always a lyric connecting ears and hearts across the continents in rhyme.
هنالك دوماً أغنيه مقفاه تعبر القارات لتصل الأذان بالقلوب
And I pray that this is the way that we will self-invent, in time.
وأنا أدعو أنها الطريقه لإكتشاف ذواتنا مع الوقت.
That's all, shukran. Thank you very much for the opportunity.
هذا كل شئ. شكراً جزيلاً لهذه الفرصه.
Okay? Great.
حسناً؟ عظيم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you all very much. It was lovely.
شكراً جزيلاً لكم جميعاً. كان هذا جميلاً.
Thank you for having me.
شكراً لإستضافتي.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Thank you very, very much. I love you.
شكراً جزيلاً، كثيراً، أحبكم.
Well, you have to let me say this.
حسناً، دعوني أقول هذا.
I just -- thank you.
فقط.. شكراً لكم.
I want to thank Chris and Jacqueline, and just everyone for having me here.
أود أن أشكر كريس و جاكلين، والجميع لإستضافتي.
It's been a long time coming, and I feel like I'm home.
لقد كان وقتاً طيباً، ولقد أحسست بأنني في منزلي،
And I know I've performed for some of your companies
وأعرف أنني قدمت عروضي لبعض من شركاتكم
or some of you have seen me elsewhere,
وبعضكم قد رأني في مكان ما
but this is honestly one of the best audiences I've ever experienced.
لكن بصدق هذا من أفضل الجماهير التي مرت علي
The whole thing is amazing, and so don't you all go reinventing yourselves any time soon.
الحدث بكامله مدهش، وإياكم أن تعيدو إختراع أنفسكم في القريب.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)